let's just do some love men because we
can try to finish what I was planning to
teach okay all right need by chilla
right you bet you're like Elsa so Amy
this is the second of the positive
refuge class what was the first negative
one
[Music]
yeah if you take refuge in Buddha don't
don't waste your time with things that
don't work the second one yeah once you
take refuge in Dharma don't hurt other
people being third one once you take
refuge in Sangha don't hang out with
losers okay
first positive one
yeah any image of Buddha consider it
real Buddha okay respect it like real
good okay now we reached Dahmer we must
still be on individual okay okay
Petula Casasola me once you go to refuge
in the Dharma you cannot eat in China
took on John Malkovich a girl you have
to respect even a single letter written
on a piece of paper as if it was the
jinkin diamond cutter Sutra
okay thanks because difficult like
you're not supposed to step on a letter
then in New York the newspapers are
flying everywhere on the ground and you
have to dance okay are in some countries
they put words in the sidewalk or
it gets a little crazy but the idea is
to express the Dharma you need letters
okay
you can't teach down where we got
letters you can't write it down a book
without letters
therefore letters become holy okay and
we shouldn't disrespect better so now in
English day I'll teach you a new word
shoppings
it's called officious officious means
you go to a Dharma event there are some
old students there and you put the paper
on the floor and they go let me teach
you you are a bad person you know you
put the paper on the floor you know I am
the older student I will teach you you
are very stupid you know and then they
make everybody feel bad that they make
all the new students feel stupid and
then and the new student often goes away
and doesn't come back that happened to
me a lot when I was first become a
Buddhist I met this kind of officious
people it means that they're like Dharma
cop yeah Dharma policeman and it doesn't
feel nice you know so don't become like
that okay don't say oh you're bad person
you put the book on the floor you know
it's supposed to be joyful and happy and
you don't have to practice for other
people because it's so much work to
practice for yourself okay
okay so don't just in your own life
quietly I like to do that you know like
I put my computer away for the night and
then I'll put a coffee cup on it you
know and then I'm like that's a lot of
Dharma in there you know I don't make
announcement I just I did you know you
know and I respect it that's all so it
should be small quiet do it for yourself
respect your Dharma books expect your
demo papers yes to them yeah
that gets complicated like the packaging
on food and stuff like that what I do to
be honest I will keep two separate
garbage cans the people who know my
house one is in the laundry room and one
is in the kitchen and then the laundry
room stuff that's all written you know
like not doing papers with writing us
get on got food on them and stuff like
that then those I I keep Stephanie and I
throw them in the same garbage can when
the garbage truck comes they both go
into the same big okay but it's I keep
the dirty things together and I keep
them dharmaiah things and the easily
kept packaging and stuff I keep in a
different bag and that's as far as I
want to take it you know I don't want to
spend all my time peeling labels off of
oranges and making sure that in letters
go in
I have a limit and I think it's a happy
limit for me you know so you find your
own limit I don't have time I don't want
to spend the whole day peeling letters
off of things but I respect you know so
I actually I try to not put things on
top of my computer and and I think
Adamas inside and that's enough in my
opinion but you find your own place you
know
the main thing is that you think about
it yeah how I mean I don't want to make
you crazy right that's what the Buddha
says in the diamond cutter suture I
don't want to make you crazy
but to see a single letter on a piece of
paper you are one in a billion
creatures you are one in a billion
beings to see a letter and understand it
to see letters put together into Dharma
you are one in a hundred billion living
beings you know you are you are
extremely rare person to see one page of
gym canteen you are one time you are
lucky then you got too many times you
know you they are not again
so this letters are rare in the in the
universe you are extremely rare okay
okay so generate to enjoy children
uncommon good so they Tomatina if you
don't respect your Dharma materials set
up may set up the Lansing chemo partner
for many lifetimes you will become a
being who cannot understand letters okay
you can see them but you know you don't
understand what they are or what they
mean
okay so can should you check you have a
lot of serious problems
okay Shaarawy CNA run talk to that
symbol
Gita took the children tomorrow mokuba
shut up tell me junior
so when we make I could make line of
make light is another in English idiom
it means it doesn't mean make light it
means soft joke soft joke about somebody
so it's not critical it's just like that
llama looks like Yoda you know like
there is a llama who looks a lot like
Yoda
it was killing Liberty he looks just
like in fact I heard that they made Yoda
from his face yeah but uh but you you
shouldn't say like even soft jokes you
see like I don't know that llama looks
like I don't know Elvis Presley or
something I don't know just don't make
little jabs he said if you make little
jokes about Sirius beings then it harms
your thinking capacity okay got it
okay all right doing moombahton take Big
Eight choking more make you muscle villa
do name on that he says did that Lama
said how he said mr. stupid
please don't collect new reasons to be
stupid if you get more stupid than you
are stupid now how hard is your life
going to be exactly okay some like that
okay day I mean them mukarat negations I
mean a Dumbo Tong today if you come into
a room and there's a hundred dollar bill
on the floor and there's a little piece
of diamond cutter suit on the floor
which one will you get excited about
[Laughter]
look you can tell your friends I found
what hundred dollars on the floor or I
found a piece of Scripture on the floor
okay you can check double time today no
chuckles salsa for my Torah you're
burning but subsidy maybe if we see some
money fell in the toilet
we will try to give it like a hundred
dollars on the toilet you like even if
it's put within I can wash my hands okay
but if you drop some diamond in there
you like that it's okay when job one two
days he kept Kimball Bangkok devotion
south Egyptian saddle a lot of good said
she kept Tacoma
kept good tomorrow I made a lot of notes
because this was confusing in 1890 there
was a commission to change the Tibetan
Constitution and this person was working
on it so he had papers all over his
office and people sit on the floor right
so basically when he had to go to the
toilet or something he would make very
careful stalks of paper so he would have
walked over the paper so we're not
supposed to step over
Dharma it's a it's also very serious in
tundra so we're not supposed to it's
it's supposed to be disrespectful to
step over dumber in Asia
your feet are considered dirty super
dirty and in Thailand for example
there's signs in the temples not to
point your foot at the Buddha okay like
that
okay I'm gonna you get the point in the
story I'm not going to tell you all the
words okay he he was careful not to step
over even government papers okay
he yeah that's another story
okay positive versus valid number three
soon began do consular cancer Shalini
once you've taken refuge in Sangha guru
timber and butcher Dementors a Chamber
member sarahdan converse our year kyung
Nicobar took many satsang you're
supposed to respect even a small piece
of monk's robe oh please you find on the
ground piece of monk's robe or non zero
then you're supposed to respect it like
Buddha and you don't step on it and you
don't so it's not a problem in America
in Diamond Mountain we don't have it but
in those Buddhist countries there's many
many Dharma things and it's possible you
go into like an alley and there will be
old monks robes there's so you could be
careful not to step on them and respect
them like Sangha even that color
so then again it depends on you how far
you go you know do you respect every
purple color you know every gold color
you know monks gold color do you respect
it and I think just healthy modest
personal respect you know you say oh
that that's a llama color in your heart
you can say oh nice margin nice I like
your sweater you know and and in your
mind you can honor it but but don't be
officious you can don't go around and
say you why you buy red shoes you know
that's a llama color don't step on them
put them on your honor
you know I mean now you see a convert
right to new religion in America for
example or other countries sometimes
they're just a pain in the ass okay they
just give everybody trouble you know oh
I found out this new thing you can't
wear a red color anymore
throughout all your red team's okay
Anton just throw them all out you know
I will help you and you know I've met
people like that it's just really
irritating
okay yeah no that's okay I don't want
you so just do it happily do it lightly
dirt respectfully do it inside you don't
have to bother people with your religion
okay all right and and I've seen people
fight serious fights about things like
that very serious fights like hitting
each other and things like that so it's
just crazy
I've seen terrible things and sometimes
I'd kill primary charge it again demean
Nazi salute and Simba so even a small
piece of monks were martyred some solace
Allah if it fell on the floor or you
find it in the street Kimbo dark on
shizuka-chan good day then obviously
when a person is wearing robes you
should respect those rooms ok it's not
the real soccer what's real Sangha
people who saw emptiness directly that's
all or at least people understand the
pen people who wear red robes maybe very
few of them are somewhere but we respect
the sign we respect the symbol of the
Sangha that's all sign-in book or no
Chiba don't know nor suture on the ten
wheels of Kishida bada sampica is that
flower I put there that's a sambuca
magnolias metal meteor Kyung metal
number generation did love there are
some flowers that after they get old
like jasmine or something
they still smell really good like better
than some flower right some flowers
don't smell at all
ok so an old jasmine flowers better than
a sunflower if you want smell got it
ok nettle number ambition design get on
certain mounting dick joke young moot a
ten times income they talk and a monk
who is imperfect a monkey is not perfect
it's still better than someone who's not
look or who's not keeping any religion
or they don't have any good behavior
so even it means ok monks are not
perfect but they wear the robe which
represents people who saw emptiness so
we respect them ok that's all so it
doesn't hurt to respect everybody you
can because you never know who's a
Buddha so it doesn't cost you anything
to respect somebody ok if they're
wearing red maybe they're very great
moms maybe they're very bad monk but if
you respect them it's a good habit ok ok
oh not then there's someone my gun on
you but Childress you know what happens
if you don't do that suck some kool-aid
dog means suture where the Buddha told
people please take personal
responsibility it's not something I'm
done
yeah and then double magnifying it
protostar Kiki not Tommy John if you
guys are going to go on between in the
forest or the desert don't spend all
your time worrying about other people's
fault don't go in a cabin and then sit
there and think about somebody in Long
John that you don't like when I the last
time I saw my mama before my three-year
retreat it was very sad because we lived
together for 26 years and so I'm going
to leave him for 3 years you know and he
I said what's your final advice and I'm
I'm like oh he's going to say something
cool you know I said you know I'm my
cars waiting outside I said I have to go
you know what's your final advice he
said keep your mind in the cabin then I
said anything else he said nope
try to keep your mind inside the
meditation camera don't think about
someone you don't like and Singapore and
don't let your mind go to Singapore okay
Tana duck and killer Tommy John diamond
kpop party emoji Danielle Tennyson came
meeting the better you think you are the
less likely you will get bodhichitta
okay something like that okay so don't
don't think all I'm the best meditator
in this valley
everybody should meditate like me and
then you won't make progress get the
apartment go get solid days people who
get pride gets get careless in their
practice gentleman on Napa you know me
John so even if you see a monk who is
not behaving very well kappa GG topic
talk mingle and you criticize them you
will delay your own enlightenment by
millions of years okay it means just
leave them alone you know I just avoid
them it looks like this monk is bad then
I just I just go stay in Starbucks you
know I don't stay there and say oh you
look bad you know and don't do that you
know I just avoid them okay I don't want
to delay my enlightenment maybe you're
really a stupid person or maybe you're
not but I don't I don't want to make any
bad karma so I'm just going to go take
my girlfriend and go to Starbucks you
guys you you know do whatever you're
doing you're gonna go do that I don't
want to I don't know what you're doing
and I don't want to know
I'll just go do my little translation
present and okay like them beneath them
but they'll are corny Mian this is a
principle of the teachings that you
should avoid criticizing other Buddhists
and just take care of yourself just take
care of your own you have a lot to do
inside you don't have to worry about
outside okay all right she assumed the
time and I gave up a long long time ago
you know people I go to China people you
want to meet this Buddhist group I'm
like it's okay I'm going to here because
you know I'm going to Starbucks and we
read my children I don't want to get any
you know just quiet practice nice okay
all right I need but among in La Jolla
to me so we reached guidelines which are
all three all three jewels in one okay
so now there are six more me but and we
have about 15 more minutes okay you want
to know the principle for Dharma travels
traveling just when you get over jetlag
you have to go home then you get again
okay even though we men do big Ghanaian
and yonder cancer doing me you didn't
typically go for in this what's the
second thing we do on many mornings in
the meditation what's the second thing I
often tell you to do besides relax your
right eye on your left eyes what's the
second one yeah no that's the third one
yeah first you bring them and then what
do you do yeah you think of a good
quality of them
it's I don't like to say bow down you
know it loses meaning what bow down
means think of a good colleague that you
like about them why why are they your
teacher what do you want to learn when
you say teacher there's something that
you want to become which they have so
number seven right the first of the last
six is think about the cool things of
the three tool that's all I think about
how cool they are
okay oh that's the booty in the diamond
cutter Sutra he's so cool okay it's like
when you hear a good rock and roll you
know oh man that guy is cool to pot man
that's really nice think that about
Buddha Dharma Sangha yummy ethical
attorney Condor ship Itachi negative ad
on TV kappa dom chosen non-consenting
indignant and a young young candor
chapel just thinking about their cool
qualities is a kind of message just
thinking you know i just think what
especially people have been here for
20-something years
you know there must be something you
there must be some reason there might be
something cool about these three jewels
right so think about it sometimes
okay appreciate them okay all right
second one card endemic Connie thought
she thought she could be picked here's a
word a time okay 2p HUD could say put
thank you trip means we don't have an
English word it means anything you drink
or eat okay
the first fit should go to you you take
a sip then I'll drink the rest okay like
that okay to Buddha Dharma Sangha okay
okay yeah this oh this smells so good
mutated sin and then you wait just wait
one second
you know then drink it you know but in
your mind you have to think they took
the first sip
okay then anything you eat you know
yo chow I liked it your child we had in
Taiwan
Stanley it's like that long that's a
good yo time we were playing with it so
you know you're gonna bite this your
target you taking pretty smile and then
you pretend that they go oh thanks mmm
you eat the rest okay okay got it
so always the first part to to them just
to say thank you it's just thank you
you know you're cool thanks for taking
care of me
you take the first suit okay and then
try to pause like one hundredth of a
second you know
see them and and don't be officious you
know everybody's watching me then when
you're alone you're lying okay
that's efficient just like
pain-in-the-ass Buddhism
okay so put me into first it first bite
what's a bar put very famous in the
monastery what sparked huh bar means any
impression or photograph or car or
imprint so when you make a new book you
always send the first copy to your Lama
and the name of that is far to the first
copy of the book the first sip of the
book okay it's a nice word and we don't
have it in English I don't think right
yester tricky Japanese I adore children
gender sue me you named my jibba Sato
become Tom Jaudon whatever you eat
whatever you drink anytime anything to
give the clue okay chip a birthday they
touch up open up a mission to charity Oh
Sidney Xin collimated you thinking image
cases don't pop mainland looks like my
jibba don't get lazy and you know and
say oh that's a waste of time there's a
vow against thinking that minor bells
are stupid okay there's a valid and
stinking little vows are stupid I was so
stupid you know nobody's going to drink
anything
[Music]
I'll tell you a story in America there's
you know Christmas is a big holiday and
our parents will tell us that the guy
who brings the presents named Santa
Claus he likes to come down the chimney
okay but he's supposed to be very fun so
you know even kids are like you know and
then they always tell you before you go
to sleep on the day before they say put
some milk and some cookies for Santa if
you don't put it then maybe you won't
get a bicycle the next day you know you
don't have that photo
Jesse Michael look bicycle right I don't
think you have it somebody took a photo
of me with my bike on Christmas one day
anyway
then one you know then when the kids go
to bed the parents will drink the milk
and eat the cookies and then they will
leave a little bit there and in the
morning we wake up and we're like oh wow
Santa Claus one two and then I think
every American can remember the day that
they found out mom and dad are eating
the cookies I mean every American kid
remembers that day you were like you
know I heard these kid when she told
them Santa didn't when they found out
that it didn't exist that kid said
cathodes you know Catherine he said now
he's 30 but he said mom and she said
what she said did you lie to me about
God also
he's like 5 years old huh
did you also lie to me about God then
tear is in a bad difficult position okay
anyway they really do drink and they
really do eat it okay and they take a
sip and they see emptiness more than
before okay mm-hmm thank you should -
cho cho singing minimums you think he so
don't be lazy about it my diamond and
enchanting poet in cheek and gala times
he can be did you sleep in stock day so
what should so when you meet a high Lama
in Tibet there's a lot of etiquette you
know and I was riveted super means
attendant who does the food and drinks
for a long time many years and it's a
difficult job it's what he called the
guy in the White House chief of protocol
you have to make sure the lamas all gets
and he had many important moments come
to visit him so my life was very
difficult
I made McDonald's you found a sign that
said 10 million burgers made and I used
to say I made 10 million most easy you
know so anyway when you offer tea to a
llama high Lama it's very very
complicated you know you have to put the
cop I think Japanese tea ceremony is
similar and Chinese I had a Chinese tea
so you put the cloud
and then you have to turn the cup said
they can bring it and then you have to
make a couple and then you have to pour
it's supposed to be like the elephant's
trunk and there's a word for it you know
it can't come out like this it has to go
you know if you have to pour and it has
to go like that you know so he said
don't get lazy with the Buddha
you know don't say hey man you want so
here you got it okay be a little bit
special and then then you can drink it
okay and it's up to you you know some
people are officious and they are like I
know how to do a grace you know and you
know I'm sure the Buddha is going oh my
god not again you know just give me some
of it already in my opinion it should be
friendly it should be joyful it should
be like you're offering your friend some
coffee
this morning this morning jing-mei made
me dig me or Angela who made that
Aeropress I would die for this coffee
and was the best one I tasted in like a
month you know and so I like gave some
touch in them was it you or him I'm like
take this coffee it should be like that
hey man this is so cool and don't be
like
all right it should be affectionate
Dharma should be affectionate and joyful
and not like all right and you got six
graces how many people you know I won't
Bharath you I won't ask you how many
people learn to grace during their
retreat three not bad yeah okay good I'm
good yeah nice keep it okay don't don't
leave it at Diamond Mountain
we have enough can't get home with you
using at home okay use the Grace's in at
home those are very valuable okay and
they make your life meaningful okay if
they make your life meaningful
your life will be a lot of happier if
you're remem Americans eat and drink so
much think how much good karma you're
going to make it here if you just offer
each time you know so enjoy and make it
three you know you taste this I'll press
that jing-mei made she put in a little
more than usual you know how do you like
it you know right they can taste it okay
alright then tomorrow we'll start with
nine six seven eight nine we'll start
nice now tomorrow twelve people coming
at 5:00 I'll be here at fire if you feel
tired come later I don't care it doesn't
matter okay but what are you going to
wear
I had you stay out in this Sun for three
hours you will take something back to
China you didn't want to okay so and
then keep coming to the tone Coppola
Center and have a dream ticket rest then
go back okay
take care of your skin okay so close
down to here it's going to be a little
bit cold in the morning we heard on the
weather it's going to be cold tomorrow
morning this so wear something warm and
wear a hat wear our sunglasses bring the
sunscreen okay I bring something to sit
on through or not yes question yeah yeah
stuff you want to get rid of okay all
right these are well blessed okay see
you tomorrow morning I asked one of my
llamas is it okay we did it in the
morning they said perfect okay so yes
okay I'm supposed to stall who can tell
me done nine during the fire
think about the smoke is going around
the world which is true right small
pieces are going everywhere all the
pollution from America reaches China all
the pollution in China reaches America
okay after a while and then and then it
will go out of this world so just
imagine that it's going to many places
and and then you you get a chance to do
the offering yourself make that prayer
for peace in this world okay and you
want to do mcdonough are you ready let's
do a mandala first birthday girl
yesterday did you do one yet Ava you
ready no just alright whisper in her ear
[Music]
all right mr. Tim